Guide to the Jacqueline de Jong Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Correspondence, 1955–1976; Series I; 4.8; (12 boxes)
  - General Correspondence, 1959–1976; 3.96; (10 boxes)
    - Remfeldt, Per, 1968–1969 (Box 7, Folder 186-187)
      Incoming and outgoing correspondence with Norwegian painter Per Remfeldt on behalf of the Bergens kunstforening (Bergen Art Society) regarding the organization of a 1969 exhibition featuring de Jong, Ingvald Holmefjord, and Oddvar Torsheim. Also includes related pamphlets and third-party correspondence.
    - Rhodos
      - General staff, 1964–1968 (Box 8, Folder 188-189)
      - Blaedel, Niels, 1963–1969 (Box 8, Folder 190-196)
      - Johannesen, Erik, 1964–1969 (Box 8, Folder 197-217)
      - Peeperkorn, David, 1969–1970 (Box 9, Folder 218-219)
        Includes letters between Jong and Peeperkorn, a Dutch lawyer contracted by de Jong, and third-party correspondence between Peeperkorn and Blaedel.
      - First name only, Hanne, 1965 (Box 9, Folder 220)
    - Rotterdamsche Kunstkring (Rotterdam Art Circle), 1969 (Box 9, Folder 221)
    - Rotterdamse Kunststichting (Rotterdam Art Foundation), 1969 (Box 9, Folder 222)
    - "S" general, 1962–1970 (Box 9, Folder 223-225)
    - Schade, Virtus, 1965 (Box 9, Folder 226)
    - [Schat], Peter, 1962–1964 (Box 9, Folder 227)
      Incoming correspondence from the Dutch composer and magazine contributor.
      For letters possibly addressed to Peter Schat, see also: First name only, Peter, Box 10, folder 268
    - Simonetti, Gianni-Emilio, 1965 (Box 9, Folder 228)
      Regarding obtaining copies and documentation of The Situationist Times.
    - Sohm, Hanns, 1963–1964 (Box 9, Folder 229-230)
      Largely incoming letters from the German collector of counter-cultures.
    - Sornum, Børge, 1969 (Box 9, Folder 231)
    - Speck, Paul, 1963–1966 (Box 9, Folder 232)
    - Spectrum Film (Firm: Amsterdam, Netherlands), 1964–1965 (Box 9, Folder 233)
      Most letters are signed by Dutch film director Louis van Gasteren.
    - [Spoerri], Daniel, 1966–1975 (Box 9, Folder 234)
    - Steinbüchel-Rheinwall, Rambald von, 1966 (Box 9, Folder 235)
    - Streep, Jon Nicholas, 1968 (Box 9, Folder 236)
    - "T" general, 1964–1968 (Box 9, Folder 237)
    - Themerson, Stefan, 1962 (Box 9, Folder 238)
    - Thorsen, Jens Jørgen, 1964 (Box 9, Folder 239)
      Thorsen was a Danish artist associated with the Second Situationist International, and collaborator of Jørgen Nash.
      See also: Jørgen Nash, Box 7, folders 171-172
    - Tomaszewski, Lech, 1963–1965 (Box 9, Folder 240)
    - "U"-"V" general, 1962–1967 (Box 9, Folder 241)
    - Vacchini, Livio, 1966–1967 (Box 9, Folder 242)
    - Vandercam, Serge, 1962 (Box 9, Folder 243)
    - Voss, Jan, 1965–1966 (Box 9, Folder 244)
    - Vrijman, Jan, 1961 and undated (Box 9, Folder 245)
    - "W" general, 1961–1972 (Box 9, Folder 246)
    - Wagemaker, Jaap, 1964 (Box 9, Folder 247)
    - Welling, Dolf, 1964–1968 (Box 9, Folder 248-249)
    - Wenger, Henri, 1963–1967 (Box 9, Folder 250)
    - Wøller, Ebba, 1965–1969 (Box 9, Folder 251-252)
    - Zee, Geert H. van der, 1968–1969 (Box 9, Folder 253-254)
    - Zimmer, H. P. (Hans-Peter), 1961–1966 (Box 9, Folder 255-259)
      Incoming and outgoing correspondence with the Gruppe SPUR painter and sculptor, accompanied by an original drawing on a 1962 newspaper (stored separately in box 29) and photographs of paintings by Zimmer dated 1963.
      - Accompanying newspaper with original drawing, 1962 (Box 29, Folder 506a)
    - Third-party correspondence (Box 10, Folder 260)
    - Unidentified and partially-identified correspondence
      - First name only, general, circa 1960-1970 (Box 10, Folder 261-265)
      - First name only, Hans, 1962–1970 (Box 10, Folder 266)
        Outgoing correspondence in Dutch, possibly to Hans Elgenza, Hans Ludwig C. Jaffé, or Hans Sonnenberg (of Galerie Delta).
      - First name only, Mike, 1962–1963 (Box 10, Folder 267)
        Incoming and outgoing correspondence in English, with a painter and distributor of The Situationist Times in London.
      - First name only, Peter, 1964–1967 (Box 10, Folder 268)
        Outgoing correspondence in Dutch, possibly to Peter Schat or Peter ten Hoopen.
      - Last name only, Küthe / Kühle, 1967 (Box 10, Folder 269)
      - Last name only, Mataigne, 1968 (Box 10, Folder 270)
      - Last name only, Stöver, 1968 (Box 10, Folder 271)
      - Last name only, Wilson, 1967 (Box 10, Folder 272)
      - Unidentified, circa 1960-1970 (Box 10, Folder 273-275)
      - Letter fragments, circa 1960-1970 (Box 10, Folder 276)
  - Family Correspondence, 1955–1975; .83; (2 boxes)
    Subseries II. Family Correspondence contains correspondence in Dutch between de Jong and her family members residing in the Netherlands and Switzerland. The bulk of the letters are from her mother Alice, with a smaller number from her father Hans, her younger brother Philip, and her aunt Erna. There also are numerous manuscript letters by de Jong to her family from October 1957 to March 1968. Most of those outgoing letters date from 1961-1962, and there is a gap between December 1962 and October 1966.
    - Jong, Alice de, 1961–1975 (Box 11, Folder 277-294)
    - Jong, Erna de, 1968 (Box 11, Folder 295)
    - Jong, Hans de, 1957–1969 (Box 12, Folder 296-301)
    - Jong, Philip de, 1961–1969 (Box 12, Folder 302-308)
    - Outgoing letters, 1957–1968 (Box 12, Folder 309-320)
      Autograph and typed letters by de Jong addressed collectively to her mother, father, and brother, or sometimes simply to her "liefjes".
    - Unidentified, 1955–1969 (Box 12, Folder 321)
- The Situationist Times Records, 1962–1970; Series II; 2.29; (6 boxes)
  Series II. The Situationist Times Records documents the production of de Jong's magazine and, to a lesser extent, its distribution. Extent documents vary for each of the six published issues, but generally include research notes and outlines, source material for collages, article submissions, original maquettes, and distribution lists. Source material to be reproduced in the magazines comprises copies of archival photographs of historic buildings and museum objects, original photographs by de Jong, and magazine and newspaper clippings. Unless noted otherwise, the texts submitted to de Jong for publication in the magazine and contained in this series are generally typescripts with little to no editorial corrections. The series also includes materials to be included in a seventh issue of the magazine on the theme of "Wheels", which was never published, as well as general notes, clippings, administrative documents, and financial records pertaining to the magazine.
  Series II is arranged by issue number, followed by general records at the end.
  - Issue no. 1
    - Draft by Jacqueline de Jong, "Critique on the political practise of détournement", holograph, [1962] (Box 13, Folder 322)
    - Maquette, [1962] (Box 13, Folder 323-324)
    - Printed copy, 1962 (Box 13, Folder 325)
  - Issue no. 2
    - Receipts and distribution notes for issues no. 1-2, 1962 (Box 13, Folder 326)
    - Outline and notes for issue, [1962] (Box 13, Folder 327)
    - Article submissions
      - Gasché, Rodolphe. "Zum SPUR Prozess", [1962] (Box 13, Folder 328)
      - Vian, Boris. Musical score and lyrics for "Le Prisonnier", [1962] (Box 13, Folder 329)
  - Issue no. 3 ("Knots")
    - Research notes, [1962] (Box 13, Folder 330)
    - Notes and drawings relating to topology, [1962] (Box 13, Folder 331)
    - Article submissions
      - Bucaille, Max. "The Dog's Curse", collage, [1962] (Box 13, Folder 332)
        Accompanied by a letter from Bucaille.
      - Ehrenzwig, Anton "Meditation on the future of art", typescript with manuscript corrections, [1962] (Box 13, Folder 333)
      - Hay, George. "A short trip to chaos", [1962] (Box 13, Folder 334)
      - Themerson, Stefan. "St.Francis and the Wolf of Gubbio", maquette of opera score, 1962 (Box 26, Folder 496)
        Accompanied by a letter from Themerson.
      - "Topological study of the curve of Hoppe, of the knot, and of the Ribbon of Moebius", two manuscripts, [1962] (Box 13, Folder 335)
        Two copies, in de Jong's hand and in an unidentified hand, likely an English translation of a text by Max Bucaille.
    - Maquette, [1962] (Box 13, Folder 336-339)
    - Contact sheet, [1962] (Box 13, Folder 340)
    - Photographs and source material, [1962] (Box 13, Folder 341-342)
  - Issue no. 4 ("Labyrinths")
    - Address list for distribution, [1963] (Box 14, Folder 343)
    - Research notes, [1963] (Box 14, Folder 344-345)
    - Table of contents, illustration index, and bibliography drafts, [1963] (Box 14, Folder 346)
    - Article submissions
      - Doets, H. C. "Extract of literature found on the subject of 'A Egyptian Tarot'", typescript with corrections, [1963] (Box 14, Folder 347)
        See also: Series I. Correspondence, Doets, H. C., Box 3, folder 63
      - Doets, H. C. "Contributions très petite à l'interprétation du tarot […]", [1963] (Box 14, Folder 348)
      - Eyck, Aldo van. "Beyond visibility", holograph and typed drafts, [1963] (Box 14, Folder 349-350)
      - Fazakerley, Gordon. "Labyrinth project", [1963] (Box 14, Folder 351)
      - Jaffé, Hans. ["Les labyrinthes"], [1963] (Box 14, Folder 352)
      - Jong, Jacqueline de. "Luxor or martyr", [1963] (Box 14, Folder 353)
      - Mazman, Edward. "No happy returns for me", [1963] (Box 14, Folder 354)
      - Mazman, Edward. "A seeker of labyrinths", [1963] (Box 14, Folder 355)
      - Schat, Peter. "Labyrint - een soort opera", [1963] (Box 14, Folder 356)
      - Tomaszewski, Lech. "Nonorientable surfaces", [1963] (Box 14, Folder 357)
    - Photographs and source material, [1963] (Box 14, Folder 358-366)
      Includes a photograph by Daniel Spoerri. May also include source materials reproduced in issue no.5 and no.7.
    - Contact sheets, and negatives, [1963] (Box 14, Folder 367-368)
    - Newspaper clippings on Peter Schat's opera Labyrint, 1963–1964 (Box 29, Folder 506)
    - Review of the issue in the ICA bulletin, no. 133, 1964 (Box 14, Folder 369)
  - Issue no. 5 ("Ring and Chains")
    - Promotional material and distribution list, [1964] (Box 15, Folder 370-371)
      Includes multiple autograph drafts of an introductory letter to the issue.
    - Binding invoices from J. A. Petersen, 1964 (Box 15, Folder 372)
    - Article submissions
      - Bucaille, Max. "Cosmogonies annulaires," "Structures d'anneau," and other texts (Box 26, Folder 497-498)
      - Doets, H. C. "Some mathematical aspects", 1964 (Box 15, Folder 373)
        With accompanying correspondence.
      - Emmerich, David Georges. "Tournures", [1964-1965] (Box 15, Folder 374)
        With accompanying correspondence and schematic images, as well as a printing of Emmerich's article "Constructions autotendantes".
      - Jorn, Asger. "Art and orders: On treason, the mass action of reproduction, and the great artistic mass effect", [1964] (Box 15, Folder 375)
      - Schade, Virtus. "Forgotten Knowledge of the Universe in the Children's Hopscotch", [1964] (Box 15, Folder 376)
      - Tomaszewski, Lech. "Regular forms of closed non-orientable surfaces", [1964] (Box 15, Folder 377)
    - Maquette, [1964] (Box 16, Folder 378-385)
    - Photographs and source material, [1964] (Box 16, Folder 386-388)
      - Oversize materials (Box 28, Folder 500-501)
    - Addendum to the issue, printed, 1965 (Box 16, Folder 389)
      Accompanied by the ICA Bulletin, no. 144 (February 1965), containing review of the issue.
  - Issue no. 6 (Lithographs)
    - Call for submissions, [1967] (Box 17, Folder 390)
    - Outline of the issue, [1967] (Box 17, Folder 391)
    - Original lithographs, [1967] (Box 17, Folder 392-400)
      Lithographs by Pierre Alechinsky, Jacqueline de Jong, Asger Jorn, Wilfredo Lam, Roberto Matta, Antonio Saura, Topor, and Jan Voss.
    - Mailing list and invoices, [1967] (Box 17, Folder 401)
    - Press review list and promotional material, [1967] (Box 17, Folder 402)
  - Issue no. 7 ("Wheels")
    - Notes and drawings, undated (Box 17, Folder 403)
    - "Peter Mayer Practical Chemistry", 1966–1968 (Box 17, Folder 404-407)
      Original grouping of documents relating to spirals and wheels, perhaps for inclusion in issue no. 7. Includes a notebook collating photographs and drawings, short holograph texts on wheels, a letter dated 1966 July 8 from Dutch writer Peter ten Hoopen to Jong, and other material.
    - Photographs and source material
      - "Wheels", undated (Box 17, Folder 408-411)
      - "Wiel - no. 7, never made", undated (Box 18, Folder 412-414)
      - "ST 7 Wheels", undated (Box 18, Folder 415-416)
      - Unlabeled album, undated (Box 18, Folder 417)
      - Other photographs and source material, undated (Box 18, Folder 418-424)
  - General records
    - Notes on distribution of the magazine, circa 1962-1967 (Box 19, Folder 425)
    - Miscellaneous notes, circa 1962-1968 (Box 19, Folder 426)
      Holograph and typed notes with sketches related to the magazine and to de Jong's artwork, accompanied by a photograph and The Something Else Newsletter vol. 1, no. 7 (January 1968).
    - Newspaper clippings, photocopies, 1963–1965 (Box 19, Folder 427)
      Includes reviews of the magazine and articles on de Jong.
      - Restricted fragile originals, 1963-1965 (Box 31, Folder 517)
    - Publishing contract with Rhodos, 1964 (Box 19, Folder 428)
    - Expense reports, 1963–1969 (Box 19, Folder 429)
    - Rhodos invoices, 1965–1968 (Box 19, Folder 430)
    - Miscellaneous invoices, 1962–1968 (Box 19, Folder 431)
    - Crédit Lyonnais bank statements and credit advices, 1967–1970 (Box 19, Folder 432-433)
    - "Documents relating to the initial period of The Situationist Times", 1962 (Box 19, Folder 434)
      "MUTANT" tract anonymously published by Asger Jorn and Guy Debord, and two documents related to Peter Schat's musical composition "Entelechie II."
      Originally included letters from Rodolphe Gasché, now in Series I. Correspondence, Box 4, folder 95
- Writings, 1962–1983; Series III; 2.01; (3 boxes)
  Organized into two subseries: Writings of Jacqueline de Jong, and Writings of Others.
  Series III. Writings contains works, largely from the early 1960s, by Jacqueline de Jong, Asger Jorn, and Guy Atkins.
  - Writings of Jacqueline de Jong, 1962–1983; 1.59; (2 boxes)
    Arranged alphabetically by title.
    The subseries contains original artist's books, drafts of short texts, notes, and sketches. Several short texts contain theoretical discussions of situationism and express how de Jong positioned herself and her magazine against her contemporaries. The original and unique artists' books document a lesser-known facet of de Jong's creative work in the early 1960s. The books combine illustrations by de Jong, and texts authored by her or in collaboration with other writers, such as Dutch author Jan Holsbergen. Also included are the woodcuts and notes for de Jong's the book project The Case of the Ascetic Satyr, co-authored with Asger Jorn.
    - "Asger Jorn", text for the Barbican Art Gallery show, draft, holograph, 1983 (Box 20, Folder 435)
    - Les aventures Vskaye ou les alouettes sur Ie canapé, original artist's book, 1962 (Box 20, Folder 436)
      Features twenty original drawings in crayon, ink, and pastel. Front and back cover decorated with artworks in gouache, ink, and pastel.
    - The Case of the Ascetic Satyr, artist's book project, 1962 (Box 27, Folder 499)
      Set of eleven woodcuts by de Jong accompanied by manuscript notes by de Jong and Asger Jorn written on exhibition flyers, hotel stationery, reused paper, and napkins. After de Jong created the woodcuts in 1962, Jorn wished to publish them in a novel with accompanying text, which the pair drafted over the next years in the form of playful notes on any material at hand.
    - Chanson du pouvoir inattendu, original artist's book, circa 1962 (Box 20, Folder 437)
      In a handsewn binding featuring sixteen pages of manuscript text, original ink drawings, and woodcuts.
    - "Declaration of creative work", drafts, typescript, 1965 (Box 20, Folder 438-439)
      Editorial statement on de Jong's departure from the Internationale situationniste and her opposition towards the Scandinavian Bauhaus Situationists. Accompanied by a typescript draft discussing Jørgen Nash and Jens Jørgen Thorsen, as well as a variety of situationist writings by identified and unidentified authors, typed or recorded in de Jong's handwriting. These include "The struggle for the control of the new techniques of conditions" (notes on Guy Debord's Rapport sur la construction des situations, 1957) and "Intervention von Wolman, Deligierter der internaitonalen Lettristen am Kongres in Alba, September 1956".
    - Dream book, manuscript notebook, 1962 (Box 20, Folder 440)
      Front and back cover decorated with a signed gouache artwork.
    - "Development of the Situation of the Situationist Times from 1962 untill today", draft, typescript, undated (Box 20, Folder 441)
      Accompanied by holograph notes.
    - Electron, original artist's book, 1964 (Box 20, Folder 442)
      Features original drawings in ink and gouache by de Jong and the typed poem "Elektron" by Jan Holsbergen. Accompanied by two manuscript letters from Holsbergen.
    - "Loodgieters en Ambivalentie", draft, typescript with holograph corrections, 1963 (Box 20, Folder 443)
    - "To the martyrs of the tractionists", autograph and typed drafts, undated (Box 20, Folder 444)
    - "The Vicious Circle—or the Trialectical Development in European Art," typed drafts with manuscript corrections, undated (Box 20, Folder 445-446)
      The text contains de Jong's editorial explanations of The Situationist Times issues no. 3-5.
    - "Wahlkönig of prise de position", drafts, typescript, 1965 (Box 20, Folder 447)
    - Untitled notebook, circa 1965-1966 (Box 20, Folder 448)
      Contains various notes, including on situationism, and sketches.
    - Untitled sketchbook, 1964 (Box 20, Folder 449)
      Contains ten signed drawings in blue pen.
  - Writings of Others, 1962–1963; .42; (1 box)
    Arranged alphabetically by author.
    - Atkins, Guy. "New York Diary", typescript, 1962 (Box 21, Folder 450)
      Accompanied by a manuscript letter from Atkins to Asger Jorn.
    - Jorn, Asger. "Held & Hasard", proofs, [1963] (Box 21, Folder 451-451a)
      Two incomplete sets of proofs and manuscript pages for Jorn's book (Copenhagen: Borgens Forlag, 1963).
    - Jorn, Asger. "Ting og polis", maquette, 1963 (Box 21, Folder 452)
      Original maquette for Jorn's book (Copenhagen: Borgens Forlag, 1964), containing proof pages with holograph corrections.
    - Jorn, Asger. Miscellaneous drafts and notes, Circa 1965-1970 (Box 21, Folder 453-454)
      Fragmentary drafts and notes, in manuscript and typescript. Accompanied by photographs of exhibitions and artworks, and newspaper clippings about Jorn.
      - Accompanying clippings, 1968–1970 (Box 28, Folder 502)
- Subject Files, 1957–1979; Series IV
  Series IV. Subject Files contains notes, original texts, tracts, newspapers, other printed matter, letters, and photographs dating largely from the 1960s on topics related to situationism, the avant-garde art group Gruppe SPUR, and the protests of May 1968 in Paris. The materials were generally found together, either in labeled topical files or in the same original boxes.
  Organized into three subseries: Situationism, Gruppe SPUR, and Protests of May 1968.
  - Situationism, 1957–1979
    The subseries contains files documenting exhibitions, conferences, and publications spearheaded by the Internationale situationiste and related groups. Of particular interest are de Jong's notes from the fifth Internationale Situationniste conference in Göteborg, Guy Debord's mock-up for his idea of the English-language magazine that would become The Situationist Times, and theoretical texts in draft or printed form.
    - Account for exhibition in Odense (Denmark), 1962 (Box 22, Folder 455)
      Carbon copy of a manuscript letter by de Jong addressed to the Scandinavian section of the Second Situationist International containing biographical information, painting dimensions, and painting prices for an upcoming exhibition in Odense, Denmark.
    - "Amsterdam-Stedelijk Exhibition I.S.", undated (Box 22, Folder 456)
      Photocopies of original letters and press clipping related to the Situationist International exhibition at the Stedelijk Museum, Amsterdam (1960). Correspondents include Asger Jorn, Guy Debord, W. Sandberg, and Hans Jaffé
    - "Dossier Debord Sit. Times "Entwürfe" 1960-1961" (Box 22, Folder 457)
      Contains a mock-up of Guy Debord's planned version of Situationist Times no. 1, accompanied by typescript copies in French and English, with manuscript corrections, of the text "L'absence et ses habilleurs" / "The absence and its inhabitents."
    - "Dossier Göteborg-Konferenz", 1961 (Box 22, Folder 458)
      Contains documents related to the fifth Internationale Situationniste conference in Göteborg, Sweden, in August 1961, including notes and drawings by de Jong; a typescript "Propositions pour un programme d'action", and a press clipping.
    - "Dossier ICA, London 1960" (Box 22, Folder 459)
      Contains the ICA Bulletin no. 107 (1960 Sept./Oct.), a postcard and letter from Guy Debord; and a postcard from Asger Jorn, Guy Debord, and Hans-Peter Zimmer inviting de Jong to the ICA meeting.
    - "Dossier I.S. Tracts, Flugblätter, Interna", 1962 (Box 22, Folder 460)
      Contains Situationist International texts: a typed draft with manuscript corrections and a printed copy of "Nicht Hinauslehnen!" by de Jong, Jorgen Nash, and Ansgar Elde; the printed tract "Proclamation from l'Internationale Situationniste!"; and the typescript of "Résolution adoptée par la 4e session du C.C. de l'I.S.".
    - "Dossier Mutant Debord and Jorn", 1962 (Box 22, Folder 461)
      Contains texts related to Mutant, an association between Guy Debord and Asger Jorn: several typed and manuscript drafts of the tract "European critique of the academic association of universities, colleges, and research institutes [….]" in French and English accompanied by the printed copy of the tract, and a typed draft of "Considérations générales pour la revue Mutant" with a manuscript postcript by Michèle Bernstein.
    - "Tracts and documents"
      Printed material relating to the Internationale Situationniste's theoretical foundations and its exclusion of Gruppe SPUR and Attila Kotanyi.
      - Internationale lettriste, Internationale lettriste, no. 3, 1953 (Box 28, Folder 503)
      - Internationale Situationniste, Aux poubelles de l'histoire!, 1962 (Box 28, Folder 504)
      - Olmo, Walter, Rapporto informativo su: come non si comprende l'acte musicale, circa 1957 (Box 22, Folder 462)
      - Tracts, 1960–1962 (Box 22, Folder 463)
        Includes "Nicht Hinauslehnen" by the I.S.'s central committee, "Déclaration sur les procès contre l'Internationale Situationniste en Allemagne fédérale", "Hands off Alexander Trocchi", "Préliminaires pour une définition de l'unité du programme révolutionnaire", and "Sur l'exclusion d'Attila Kotanyi".
    - Photographs "Dossier Pinot-Gallizio", undated (Box 22, Folder 464)
      Reprints of black-and-white photographs of Giuseppe Pinot-Gallizio with de Jong in his studio.
    - Photographs, miscellaneous, 1979 and undated (Box 22, Folder 465)
      Four photographic prints, including two of Swiss artist Daniel Spoerri and de Jong.
  - Gruppe SPUR, 1961–1967